Inventory of the Crawford F. Sams papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Crawford F. Sams papers
1915-1978
79066
Hoover Institution Archives
15 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box, 11 envelopes, 1 oversize folder (8.3 linear feet)
The Crawford F. Sams papers contain correspondence, orders, speeches and writings, research data, printed matter, certificates, and photographs relating to American military medical activities in the Middle East during World War II, American military medical activities in the Korean War, Allied public health activities in occupied Japan, and scientific research on the effects of radiation.
Sams, Crawford F.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items, computer media, and digital files. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos, films, or digital files during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1979.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1902 April 1 Born, East St. Louis, Illinois
1922 January Enlisted as private in 159th Infantry, California National Guard
1924 December Army Medical Postgraduate School, Walter Reed
1925 Graduated, Field Artillery School at Fort Sill B.S. Psychology, University of California Berkeley
1927 M.S. Neurology, Washington University of St. Louis
1929 M.D., Washington University of St. Louis Assistant radiologist, Letterman General Hospital
1932 Instructor, Medical Field Service, Carlisle, Pennsylvania
1934 Director of department, Medical Field Service, Carlisle
1937 Assistant department surgeon, Department of U.S. Army, Panama Canal
1939 Medical instructor, Infantry School, Fort Benning, Columbus, Georgia
1941 Chief surgeon, United States Army Forces in the Middle East (USAFIME), Cairo, Egypt
1944 Chief of Research and Development, War Department General Staff, Washington D.C.
1945 Chief of Public Health and Welfare Section of the General Headquarters, Supreme Command Allied Powers, U.S. Army, Japan
1946-1951 Atomic Bomb Casualty Commission, Japan
1950 Chief of Public Health and Welfare Section, General Headquarters, Supreme Commander Allied Power for Japan, Tokyo, Japan
1951-1953 Member, Army Medical Board
1954-1955 Member, Special Board for the Army Surgeon General
1955 Retired from military Research physician, University of California Berkeley Operations Research Center and University of California San Francisco Department of Neurology
1962 Research physician and professor, University of California Berkeley
1961-1963 Medical director, Institute of Medical Physics, University of California Berkeley
1994 December 2 Died
Scope and Contents
The Crawford F. Sams papers contain correspondence, orders, speeches and writings, research data, printed matter, certificates, and photographs relating to American military medical activities in the Middle East during World War II, American military medical activities in the Korean War, Allied public health activities in occupied Japan, and scientific research on the effects of radiation.
Original folder titles and arrangement were maintained. Unless otherwise noted, Sams is the author of writings within the collection. Materials in boxes 9 to 15 relate to Sams' radiation research.
United States. Army--Officers.; United States. Army Medical Service.; Korean War, 1950-1953--Medical care.; Medicine, Military--United States.; Public health--Japan.; Radiation.; World War, 1939-1945--Medical care.; World War, 1939-1945--Middle East.; Japan--History--Allied occupation, 1945-1952.
- "Medic," autobiography of Crawford F. Sams, undated (Box-folder 1: 1-6)
- Military record, 1923-1966 (Box-folder 2: 1-3)
- Military file, 1953 May (Box-folder 2: 4)
- Retirement, 1955 (Box-folder 2: 5)
- News clippings, 1939-1955 (Box-folder 2: 6)
- "The Impact of Hiroshima and Nagasaki on Military Medical Operations,", 1957 (Box-folder 2: 7)
- "The Contribution of General Crawford F. Sams to the Occupation of Japan, 1945-1951," Ann Crusa Wyman, M.A. thesis, 1975 May (Box-folder 2: 8)
- Printed matter and clippings relating to Brookhaven National Laboratory, 1960-1961 (Box-folder 2: 9)
- Miscellaneous, 1953-1955 (Box-folder 3: 1-2)
- Printed matter and clippings on public health activities in Japan, 1946-1955 (Box-folder 3: 3)
- Press releases, 1953-1955 (Box-folder 3: 4)
- Russia Institute notes, 1965 (Box-folder 3: 5)
- "The Middle East Countries,", 1960-1962 (Box-folder 3: 6)
  Scope and Contents note
  A section of a U.S. Army Medical Service history of medical activities in World War II.
- Speeches and papers, 1953-1955 (Box-folder 3: 7)
- "Are We Using All Our Weapons Against Tuberculosis?," Albert and Mary Lasker Foundation, 1954 (Box-folder 3: 8)
- Address given at the dedication program, 1960 January (Box-folder 3: 9)
- Requests for reprints, "Experiences in Immunization Against TB with BCG Vaccines in Japan,", 1951-1955 (Box-folder 3: 10)
- Personal file, 1943 August - 1952 October (Box-folder 4: 1-4)
- Biographical sketch, 1952-1973 (Box-folder 4: 5)
- Korean episode, 1951-1959 (Box-folder 4: 6-7)
- Personal file, 1952 November - 1954 March (Box-folder 5: 1-7)
- Personal file, 1954 April - 1955 July (Box-folder 6: 1-6)
- "Views and Recommendations Concerning Military and Civilian Planning in Time of Total War,", 1954 (Box-folder 6: 7)
- Personal files, 1955-1978 (Box-folder 7: 1-11)
- Public Health and Welfare in Japan, 1948-1952 (Box 8)
  Series of printed reports issued by Public Health and Welfare Section, General Headquarters, Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers.
- International Congress of Neurology, Vienna: "Correlation of Cation Activity with Electrophysiologic Response of CNS to Low Level Radiation,", 1965 September (Box-folder 9: 1)
- Final report, Part III: Time series, 1963-1965 (Box-folder 9: 2-3)
- Research, records, and notes, 1966-1967 (Box-folder 9: 4-6)
- Final report, Part IV: Sleep, 1966 (Box-folder 9: 7)
- Final report, Part VII: Equilibrium model, 1963-1965 (Box-folder 10: 1)
- Family shelter, 1960 November (Box-folder 10: 2)
- Paper for Acta Radiologicum (New York Symposium), Sams, Endo, Aird, et al.: "Function Response of CNS of Dogs to Low Level Radiation,", 1964 September (Box-folder 10: 3)
- Sams, C. F.: Epilepsy Symposium, Western Societies of Neurological Sciences, 1966 March (Box-folder 10: 4)
- Sams, et al.: 200 word and 1000 word abstract for American Neurological Association (Atlantic City, NJ), 1964 June (Box-folder 10: 5)
- International Symposium at California Institute of Technology, 1965 June (Box-folder 10: 6)
- Brain research: "Potassium, Sodium Ion Estimates in a Closed Vivo System Using Glass Electrodes,", 1966 (Box-folder 10: 7)
- Sams and Aird, American Electroencephalographic Society (Boston): "Spectral Analysis of Electrophysiological Response of CNS to Low Level Radiation -- and Its Significance,", 1965 June (Box-folder 10: 8-9)
- "Fallout Radiation,", 1961 January (Box-folder 11: 1)
- Final report - research project, "Central Nervous System Response to Low Level X-Irradiation," USPH Contract 86-262-160, 1965 July (Box-folder 11: 2-6)
- "The Relationship of Acute and Delayed Effects and a Suggested Method of Treatment,", 1957 May (Box-folder 11: 7-8)
- "Central Nervous System Response to Low Level X-Irradiation" and "Application of Mathematical and Computer Techniques to Complex Biological Systems,", 1967 October (Box-folder 11: 9)
- Radiation references, 1956-1966 (Box-folder 12: 1)
- EXP 98, 1967 March (Box-folder 12: 2)
- Cation graphs, 1966-1967 (Box-folder 12: 3)
- Publications of Dr. Robert Aird, 1948-1962 (Box-folder 12: 4)
- Sams, C. F. bibliography, undated (Box-folder 12: 5)
- Correspondence with Lockheed, 1964-1967 (Box-folder 12: 6)
- Radiation notes, Hawkins, undated (Box-folder 12: 7)
- Federal contract #PH-62-160: "Studies of the Action of Ionizing Radiation in the Production of Acute Latent Effects in Animals and Humans,", 1963 June - 1964 June (Box-folder 12: 8)
- Proposal for epilepsy, 1965 (Box-folder 12: 9)
- Computer at UCSF and UC Berkeley, 1966 (Box-folder 12: 10)
- Proposal for Atomic Energy Commission, 1966 (Box-folder 12: 11)
- Proposal for NASA behavior, undated (Box-folder 12: 12)
- Proposal for National Institute of Neurological Disease and Blindness, 1965 (Box-folder 12: 13)
- Contract #PH 86-62-162, "Central Nervous System Response to Low Level Radiation,", 1959-1962 (Box-folder 12: 14)
- Dr. J. B. Drori's proposal, undated (Box-folder 12: 15)
- Renewal request: United States Department of Health, Education, and Welfare -- CNS Low Level Radiation, Sams, 1964 June - 1965 June (Box-folder 13: 1)
- General correspondence, 1966 (Box-folder 13: 2)
- "Central Nervous System Response to Low Level Radiation,", 1965 July (Box-folder 13: 3-4)
- "Central Nervous System Response to Low Level X-Irradiation" and "Application of Mathematical and Computer Techniques to Complex Biological Systems,", 1967 October (Box-folder 13: 5)
- "Fallout Radiation,", 1961 January (Box-folder 13: 6)
- "Central Nervous System Response to Low Level X-Irradiation," United States Department of Health, Education, and Wellness, 1965 December (Box-folder 13: 7)
- Proposal for biomathematics, 1966 (Box-folder 13: 8)
- "Air Pollution on the Engineering Field Station,", 1957 (Box-folder 13: 9)
- Biomathematics progress report, 1962 (Box-folder 13: 10)
- Biomathematics cation data, 1965-1966 (Box-folder 13: 11)
- Electrode calibrations, 1966-1967 (Box-folder 13: 12)
- Final report, Part VI: Cation activity, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 13: 13)
- "Some Effects of Radiation on Aging" and "Biomedical Effects of Radiation Covering the Period August 31, 1959 - January 31, 1960,", undated (Box-folder 13: 14)
- Speech on "Nuclear Fallout Shelters,", 1960 (Box-folder 13: 15)
- Proposal for biomathematical research group, 1962 (Box-folder 14: 1)
- Data on Trupino, EXP 63, EXP 67, undated (Box-folder 14: 2)
- Progress report, 1963 January - March (Box-folder 14: 3)
- Progress report, 1962 July - September (Box-folder 14: 4)
- Progress report, 1962 October - December (Box-folder 14: 5)
- Final report, Part IX: Metabolism PO2- Glucose, SH-, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 14: 6)
- Final report, Part VIII: Perfusions, Na K Ca, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 14: 7)
- Supplement request: United States Department of Health, Education, and Welfare -- CNS Low Level Radiation, Sams, 1964 January (Box-folder 14: 8)
- Quarterly report, 1964 July - September (Box-folder 14: 9)
- Progress report, 1964 January - March (Box-folder 14: 10)
- Progress report, 1963 October - December (Box-folder 14: 11)
- Progress report, 1963 July - September (Box-folder 14: 12)
- Calibration notes, 1964 (Box-folder 14: 13)
- Final report, Part I: General, 1963 (Box-folder 14: 14)
- Electrode calibrations Na, 1966-1967 (Box-folder 14: 15)
- Electrode calibrations K, 1966-1967 (Box-folder 14: 16)
- Final report, Part V: Mechanisms electrodes, 1962-1964 (Box-folder 14: 17)
- Rand Symposium, 1963 (Box-folder 14: 18)
- UCLA Symposium: "Electrophysiological Changes of the Central Nervous System in response to Low Level Radiation,", 1963 August (Box-folder 14: 19)
- Report, 1965 (Box-folder 14: 20-21)
- Proposal for "Central Nervous System Response to Low Level X-Irradiation,", 1965 June (Box-folder 15: 1)
- "To Determine the Relationship of Acute and Delayed Effects of External Radiation, and the Suggested Method of Treatment,", 1957 August (Box-folder 15: 2)
- Reports on radiation, 1946-1959 (Box-folder 15: 3)
- "Contributions Toward a Mathematical Model of the Human System -- I: The Respiratory System,", 1959 September (Box-folder 15: 4)
- Medical center (proposal), National Institutes of Health, 1959 (Box-folder 15: 5)
- Rand Corporation, 1957-1961 (Box-folder 15: 6-7)
- National Institutes of Health - Operations Research Center, 1961-1967 (Box-folder 15: 8)
- American Association for the Advancement of Science (Biometrics), 1959-1960 (Box-folder 15: 9)
- Western branch of American Public Health Association Health Mobilization Committee, 1960-1961 (Box-folder 15: 10)
- California hearings, 1955-1960 (Box-folder 15: 11)
- Certificates, 1915-1971 (Box-folder 16: 1-2)
- Charts of public health statistics in Japan, undated (Box 16)
- Yasuyori Tamba, Ishimpo, collotyped copy of section of oldest surviving Japanese medical text (984 A.D.), undated (Box 16)
- 175 prints of people and scenes in the Middle East, 1942-1943 (Envelope A)
- 9 prints of groups of U.S. Army officers, and 2 prints of Crawford Sams, civilians, and medical scenes in occupied Japan, 1922-1937 (Envelope m*B)
- 116 prints of soldiers, civilians, and military and medical scenes in the Panama Canal Zone before World War II, and in the U.S. and occupied Japan after the war, undated (Envelope C-D)
- 619 prints of people, street scenes, and military and medical scenes in occupied Japan after World War II, undated (Envelope E-K, mL)